בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is קלג. Kuf Lamed Gimmel.
And we pick up with four lines from the top, the two
dots. אמר מר, Amar Mar, let's take a look. אמר מר, Amar
Mar, בשר, basar, so this is going back to the דרשה drasha
of בשר ערלתו basar orlato and we've moved on from שבת Shabbos
to talk about also צרעת, tzara'at, so we're going to focus on
that for a little bit. אמר מר, Amar Mar, בשר, basar, אף
על פי
שיש שם בהרת, af al pi sheyesh sham baheret, even though that
there is צרעת, tzara'at, you cut away, you cut it away if
there's צרעת tzara'at on the foreskin. בהרת עמו, baheret imo, you should
still cut it away. דברי רבי יהושע. Divrei Rabbi Yoshua. That's what
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yoshua says. הא
למה לי קרא? Ha lamma li krah? Now the גמרא Gemara says
why do you need a פסוק? pasuk? דבר שאינו מתכוין הוא. Davar
she'eino mitkaven hu. You're not intending to cut it away. I mean,
you're intending to just do a ברית מילה. brit milah. You're not
trying to remove the צרעת, tzara'at, that's incidental. ודבר שאינו מתכוין מותר.
Vedavar she'eino mitkaven mutar. And if you're not intending, it's permissible. Now
there's an obvious answer here which is פסיק רישא, p'sik reisha, right,
which the גמרא Gemara will get to. Anyway, let's see what the
גמרא Gemara first
says. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, it says אביי, Abaye, לא נצרכה אלא
לרבי יהודה, דאמר דבר שאינו מתכוין אסור, lo nitzrecha ela lerabbi Yehuda
de'amar davar she'eino mitkaven asur. that says אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven is
אסור. asur. So you have a פסוק pasuk to tell me that
you can't cut it away even though you're not intending and it's
incidental, I mean a פסוק pasuk to tell me that you can
cut it away, because normally even though you weren't intending would be
a problem, here it's okay. But רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava
says, אפילו תימא רבי שמעון, afilu teima Rabbi Shimon, even according to
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you need a פסוק pasuk to tell me,
otherwise this would have been a problem. Why would this have been
a problem? מודה רבי שמעון פסיק רישא ולא ימות. Modeh Rabbi Shimon
p'sik reisha velo yamut. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees that if you
cut off the head, won't it die? If you cut off the
ערלה, orlah, won't the צרעת tzara'at come off? It's a definite consequence.
So you can't say you're not intending when it's a definite consequence.
So now the גמרא, Gemara, so therefore according, if it were normal
rule, a normal case רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would not allow it,
but here he allows it because of the פסוק pasuk that מילה
milah overrides cutting צרעת. tzara'at. So now the גמרא Gemara says, ואביי
לית ליה האי סברא? ve'Abaye lith lei hai sevara? Does אביי Abaye
not agree to this reason? This qualification of רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon
position? והא אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו, veha Abaye veRava de'amrei taveihu, אביי
Abaye and רבא Rava both say, מודה רבי שמעון פסיק רישא ולא
ימות. modeh Rabbi Shimon p'sik reisha velo yamut.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees by cutting off the head and you
know, and won't it die? Meaning of course רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says it, if it's a necessary consequence you can't say it's אינו
מתכוין. eino mitkaven. So the גמרא Gemara says, בתר דשמעיה מרבא הוה
סבר.
batar d'shamei merava
hava savar. You're right. First he didn't hold of the position. First
he held that even if it was a necessary consequence רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon would say it's allowed. After he heard that רבא Rava
made this qualification in רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he was persuaded that
that was true. But this was a later position of אביי. Abaye.
In an earlier stage אביי Abaye thought that even רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon would normally allow it. So according to that you wouldn't have
needed this פסוק pasuk by ברית מילה. brit milah. You only needed
it according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says, איכא דמתני להא דאביי ורבא אהא. ika de'matni leha de'Abaye
veRava aha.
Some have this whole discussion about whether it's according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon or not and whether רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees by
פסיק רישא p'sik reisha on a different דרשה drasha relating to צרעת.
tzara'at. Not exactly ברית מילה brit milah but צרעת tzara'at of אינו
מתכוין eino mitkaven by צרעת. tzara'at. Let's take a look. הישמר בנגע
הצרעת לשמור ולעשות. Hishtamer b'nega hatzara'at lishmor vela'asot.
Watch yourself closely regarding the, you know, the spot of צרעת tzara'at
to observe it to do properly. לעשות אי אתה עושה. La'asot i
ata oseh. You cannot do an action to actively remove it. אבל
עושה אותה בסיב שעל גבי רגלו ובמוט שעל גבי כתפו. Aval oseh
otah b'seev she'al gabei raglo uv'mot she'al gabei kteifo. But what you
can do is you can wrap a, if a type of a
bandage around your leg if you're doing it to you know protect
your leg from friction and you know or other things, or you
can carry a מוט mot on your shoulder, and even though that's
right on top of where the צרעת tzara'at is, ואם עברה עברה.
ve'im avrah avrah. And if it passed, it passed. If it's incidental.
So again the understanding here being that it's not a trick but
you genuinely are not intending. But you don't have to actively avoid
doing anything that might lead to it. You can go about your
normal day and if it happens to lead to it rubbing away
or either the skin scraping off, that's not your problem. You just
can't actively and intentionally go ahead and do it. So now the
גמרא Gemara says, והא למה לי קרא? veha lamma li krah?
Why do you need a פסוק? pasuk? דבר שאינו מתכוין הוא. Davar
she'eino mitkaven hu. It's not intentional. And here it seems like not
only not intentional but not intentional and not even a necessary consequence.
ודבר שאינו מתכוין מותר. Vedavar she'eino mitkaven mutar. And something that's not
intentional is permissible. So you don't need a פסוק. pasuk. So אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, לא נצרכה אלא לרבי יהודה lo nitzrecha ela lerabbi
Yehuda, דאמר דבר שאינו מתכוין אסור. de'amar davar she'eino mitkaven asur, You
only need it for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says that even
if it's unintended
it's אסור. asur. So even though normally he would forbid things that
are unintended, here by צרעת tzara'at he would say it's permissible. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, ורבא אמר, veRava amar, רבא Rava says,
אפילו תימא רבי שמעון, afilu teima Rabbi Shimon, it could even be
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. ומודה רבי שמעון פסיק רישא ולא ימות. Umodeh
Rabbi Shimon p'sik reisha velo yamut. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree
by a פסיק רישא. p'sik reisha. Now the way it's described this
case it's not so clear that it's a פסיק רישא, p'sik reisha,
but רבא's Rava saying is this could work according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon in a case of פסיק רישא. p'sik reisha. In a
case of פסיק רישא p'sik reisha where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would
normally say it's forbidden if it's a necessary consequence, here he would
say it's not forbidden because a special פסוק pasuk tells you as
long as. As you are like not actively doing something, you're to
remove it. So even though even in cases where it is a
necessary consequence if it'll eventually rub off. Okay, Abaye אביי, Abaye, the
Gemara גמרא Gemara once again says, Abaye למאי הסברא, Abaye l'mai hasveira,
why did Abaye אביי Abaye have to run to Rabbi Yehuda רבי
יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Doesn't he agree with this idea within Rabbi Shimon
רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? ואביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו דאביי מודה רבי שמעון
בפסיק רישא ולא ימות, v'Abaye v'Rava d'amri tarveihu d'Abaye modeh Rabbi Shimon
b'psik reisha v'lo yamut, Abaye אביי Abaye and Rava רבא Rava both
say, including Abaye אביי, Abaye, that Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
would agree that if it's a necessary consequence, it's a problem. So
he could have said that this Braita ברייתא Braita was Rabbi Shimon
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and in a case where it was a
necessary consequence. So then the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, לבתר דשמעיה מרבא
סברה, l'basar d'shami meiRava sivar, fine, he was he came around to
that position after he had heard it from Rava רבא, Rava, but
initially that was not his his position. So now what the Gemara
גמרא Gemara is saying is, there are two cases where it's not
a problem of cutting off Tzara'at צרעת. Tzara'at. One is actively doing
it by a case of Brit Milah ברית מילה. Brit Milah. The
other is not actively doing it, sort of like doing other things
and it happens incidentally.
In both of those cases, you need to tell me even according
to Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that's a problem because in
the first case certainly, but even in the second case, if it's
a case of a necessary consequence, normally that would have been a
problem, but here it tells me it's okay. So again, the chiddush
חידוש chiddush that we've learned, besides the Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon issue, is in addition to actively cutting it away which is
allowed by Brit Milah ברית מילה, Brit Milah, you can do other
types of things like wearing clothing, carry poles, things that would indirectly
cause it to rub away as long as that is not your
intention, even as we've seen, even if it will necessarily happen. Now,
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this, ואביי אליבא דרבי שמעון האי
בשר מאי עביד ליה, v'Abaye aliba d'Rabbi Shimon hai basar mai avid
lei, according to the earlier position of Abaye אביי Abaye that this
was not needed according to Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that
Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say even the necessary consequence,
even not by Tzara'at צרעת, Tzara'at, all this stuff is okay. According
to that, we don't hold that way, but according to that position
that I always would have known that by everything, that if it's
not your intention, regardless of whether it'll necessarily happen, it's always okay.
Why do you need the Pasuk פסוק Pasuk by Tzara'at צרעת? Tzara'at?
It's just an application of a general rule. So what do you
do by the extra word "basar" בשר, basar, which is to tell
me what seems to be telling me you're allowed you know these
things, which according to Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we just
said is, according to Abaye's אביי Abaye's early read of Rabbi Shimon
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, which would be true anyway. So the Gemara
גמרא Gemara says, מאי עביד ליה? mai avid lei? So Amar Rav
Avin באומר לקוץ בהרת הוא מתכוין. baomer lakutz baharat hu mitkaven.
Let's say the case is, the guy's doing a Brit Milah ברית
מילה Brit Milah and he is actually saying, I am doing this
Brit Milah ברית מילה Brit Milah and I am going to also
be cutting away the Tzara'at צרעת Tzara'at and I'm very happy that
I'm cutting away the Tzara'at צרעת. Tzara'at. So he's intending. It's not
like, alright whatever, I you know I can't be held you know
it's not I mean I know I'm doing it but it's not
what I'm trying to do. Let's say he actively said I am
trying to cut away the Tzara'at צרעת Tzara'at as I cut away
the Brit Milah ברית מילה. Brit Milah. So according to this idea,
that would be permissible. As long as you're doing a Brit Milah
ברית מילה Brit Milah and you're not doing anything different because you're
cutting away the Tzara'at צרעת, Tzara'at, it doesn't matter if you are
willingly cutting away the Tzara'at צרעת Tzara'at at that time. So that
would be a nice chiddush חידוש, chiddush, but according to Rabbi Shimon
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, anything less than that according to this early
read of Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would have been taken
for granted, would have been okay in all cases and you know,
not only by Tzara'at צרעת Tzara'at and Brit Milah ברית מילה. Brit
Milah. So now the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this, תינח גדול
קטן מאי איכא למימר. tinih gadol katan mai ikka l'meimar. So that
makes sense by an adult. Because it says בשר basar if you
remember, both by an adult's Brit Milah ברית מילה Brit Milah and
by a minor's. So by adult I get that. But by a
minor, so you know the minor isn't try isn't doing his own
Brit Milah ברית מילה, Brit Milah, so what's the scenario? Now it's
not such a hard question, the Gemara גמרא Gemara gives the obvious
answer, so let's take a look. So קטן מאי איכא למימר? katan
mai ikka l'meimar? So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, Amar Rav Mesharshiya
באומר אבי הבן לקוץ בהרת הוא מתכוין. baomer avi haben lakutz baharat
hu mitkaven. Fine,
the father is saying he's trying to do it. So you might
have thought that when you are actively trying to do it, you
should not be allowed, so the Pasuk פסוק Pasuk tells you no.
Since you're doing the Brit Milah ברית מילה, Brit Milah, it doesn't
matter if you add your intention anyway, the Brit Milah ברית מילה
Brit Milah is what allows you to cut it away. ואיכא. v'ika.
So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, nevertheless, ואיכא אחר ליעבד
אחר. v'ika acher l'aveid acher. So what? If you're actively intending, if
there's another person around you should try to get the other somebody
else to do it who's not going to actively intend to do
it. Okay, at least then you won't have you know a blatant
sort of violation. Okay,
so the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, דאמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש וריש
לקיש אמר, d'amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish v'Resh Lakish she'amar, כל מקום
שאתה מוצא עשה ולא תעשה. kol makom she'ata motzeh aseh v'lo ta'aseh.
If you have a positive and a negative command conflicting against one
another, אם אתה יכול לקיים שניהם מוטב, im ata yakhol l'kayem shteihem
mutav, if you can have a way that you satisfy both, then
that's the best. ואם לאו, v'im lav, but if you can't, if
one has to give, יבוא עשה וידחה לא תעשה, yavo aseh v'idchei
lo ta'aseh, the aseh עשה aseh should override the lo ta'aseh לא
תעשה. lo ta'aseh. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara understands that's what's happening
here by the Tzara'at צרעת Tzara'at and the Brit Milah ברית מילה.
Brit Milah. Now, actually not really, because the Gemara גמרא Gemara said
before, if you remember, that the Tzara'at צרעת Tzara'at is even a
mitzvat aseh מצוות עשה. mitzvat aseh. It's not just a lo ta'aseh
לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. So it's not the standard rule of an
aseh עשה aseh overriding a lo ta'aseh לא תעשה, lo ta'aseh, because
normally that rule would not allow you to cut it away. It
is a special Pasuk פסוק Pasuk that tells you by Brit Milah
ברית מילה Brit Milah you're allowed to do it. It's not just
a general rule because again, the Tzara'at צרעת Tzara'at is more weighty
than just a lo ta'aseh לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. But the Gemara
גמרא Gemara still saying that the principle should apply. Why should we
let you, if it's like incidental, fine, but if you're actively trying
to violate the lo say then why shouldn't we try to do
it in a way which avoids this conflict? Why shouldn't we just
find somebody else who's not so committed to cutting away the צרעת
tzaraas and then it won't be as much of a direct conflict?
Okay, so yes, I get that it's allowed, but עשה דוחה לא
תעשה aseh docheh lo ta'aseh is also allowed, but not when it
can be avoided. So here too we shouldn't do it if it
could be avoided, if that direct intention should be avoided. So the
גמרא Gemara says דליכא אחר, d'leika acher, fine,
there's only one מוהל mohel around. Nobody else is around to do
it, and therefore, and this מוהל mohel is willing, is intentionally cutting
it away. So in that case you would be allowed to do
it because there's no other option. Okay, now, yes.
When they're talking about an adult and ברית מילה bris milah on
an adult, why not wait? It doesn't have to be done on
the eighth day, it's already
past.
Could be you can, you mean wait till the צרעת tzaraas clears
up.
Yeah, why would it be permitted?
So you know, that's a very good point, which is that the
חידוש chiddush that you can cut it away by צרעת tzaraas is
not just because of the urgency of the eighth day. That's your
right, as part of what...
If they say it's an adult.
Right, you're right. Part of what we learn, the fact that we
learn from this פסוק, pasuk, it's an excellent point. Part of what
we learn from this פסוק pasuk is not just that even though
צרעת tzaraas is a positive and a negative, part of what we
learn is as you said, even if in theory you could like
you know wait a few weeks till it clears up, we say
no. The fact that you're doing the ברית מילה bris milah allows
you to go ahead and to cut it.
But why would that be permitted too? I mean, it's one thing
about being מחלל שבת... mechaleil Shabbos...
No, no, no, no, we're not in the שבת Shabbos case.
No, it's
only the צרעת tzaraas case. Right now we've only looked at the
צרעת.
tzaraas. Right, I understand.
But yeah, right, I understand. But the point would be like why
delay it longer, you know, than you have to? But you're right,
it's not the urgency. It's somehow just this trump.
And nevertheless...
Right, I understand, so it's not the urgency that trumps, it's just
that the ברית מילה, bris milah, if you want to say it
like the ברית מילה bris milah somehow like redefines the nature of
what you're doing. But that's why when you intentionally try to do
it, that's when the גמרא, Gemara, you know, really sort of is
challenged. So I assume you're right. In this last stage where you're
willingly doing it, where the גמרא Gemara says get another מוהל, mohel,
why didn't the גמרא Gemara also say like you know like you
know wait? Why can't you just wait? Yeah, it's a good question.
You know, why isn't wait just as good of a point of
like get somebody else? I don't know the answer. Unless the point
is that the waiting is indefinite. You don't know if the צרעת
tzaraas will ever clear up, you know? So that could be part
of the problem, that the waiting doesn't have a clear end point.
But you're right, at this stage when you're willingly conflicting with it,
the גמרא Gemara is really pushing back and saying it's going too
far, yes.
I'm surprised there's no mention here about the severity of the penalty
for not having a ברית מילה, bris milah, which itself would have
been a reason...
וחייב כרת. v'chayav kares. Yeah, so that's also a question, when do
you get כרת? kares? Every day you get כרת kares if you
don't, or when you die without getting a ברית מילה? bris milah?
And so the גמרא Gemara will sort of get to the severity
a little bit later. But you say, but why do you need
the severity? You have a פסוק. pasuk. You're saying, so alright, anyway,
but that might be playing into this issue as well. What's also
worth noting is that even though the גמרא Gemara says that רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon agrees by פסיק רישא, psik reisha, it didn't ask
the question
of
you know, well hold on, let me just think a second. No,
no, well let me rephrase that. Even though the גמרא Gemara says
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon agrees by פסיק רישא, psik reisha, it seems
to feel that... okay, strike that again. Moving on. I mean, the
question I was going to ask, but it's not clear that you
can argue this from the גמרא Gemara is, if רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon agrees to פסיק רישא, psik reisha, does it make it worse
to intentionally intend, you know, to intend to cut it away than
to cut it away unintentionally knowing that it's going to happen? You
know, the גמרא Gemara makes it sound that to actively intend it
is still worse, although you know, whatever, it's worth thinking about that
issue. And part of that gets to the question you know that
I was just saying a minute ago to Rivka, which is that
even if it's פסיק רישא, psik reisha, you could say fundamentally it's
an act of מילה, milah, whereas once I you know once I
specifically intended, it does change the quality of the act. Anyway, what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is that you're allowed to cut away
the צרעת tzaraas if you're doing a ברית מילה, bris milah, even
if it will necessarily happen, and possibly even if you're intending to
cut away the צרעת tzaraas if there's no other options. And Rivka's
right that even if it's not an eighth day מילה milah and
you don't have that urgency. Okay, now we get onto the next
point that about back to מילה milah on שבת Shabbos or related
שבת Shabbos issues. So אמר מר, amar mar, we're quoting the ברייתא
Baraisa we quoted before, יום טוב אינו דוחה, Yom Tov eino docheh,
cutting the ברית מילה bris milah on the eighth day does not
override יום טוב, Yom Tov, אלא בזמנה, ela bizmanah, only in its
only an eighth day ברית מילה, bris milah, not if it's a
late ברית מילה; bris milah; it doesn't override יום טוב, Yom Tov,
it certainly doesn't override שבת. Shabbos. So here's the... well, not necessarily.
Anyway, here's the it's not so פשיטא peshita by יום טוב Yom
Tov because maybe you would say you know יום טוב Yom Tov
isn't as weighty as שבת, Shabbos, maybe the עשה aseh of ברית
מילה bris milah overrides לא תעשה lo ta'aseh of יום טוב. Yom
Tov. So we... it is a bigger חידוש chiddush by יום טוב
Yom Tov okay, that a late מילה milah doesn't override. So the
גמרא Gemara says מנא הני מילי, mna hani mili, where do you
know this from? So אמר חזקיה, amar Chizkiyah, says חזקיה, Chizkiyah, וכן
תנא דבי חזקיה, v'chein tana d'bei Chizkiyah, we taught from the house
of חזקיה, Chizkiyah, אמר קרא, amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says, לא
תעשה. lo ta'aseh. ממנו עד בוקר. mimenu ad boker. This is by
a קרבן korban that says you should not leave over from to
the next day. This is specifically by the קרבן פסח. korban pesach.
So don't leave over to the morning of the 15th, and then
it says, והנותר ממנו עד בוקר באש תשרופו, v'hanosar mimenu ad boker
ba'eish tisrofu, and anything left over to the morning of the 15th,
you burn it in a fire. שאין תלמוד לומר עד בוקר. she'ein
talmud lomar ad boker. Why does it say until the morning a
second time? Why does it say לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר, lo
sosiru mimenu ad boker, והנותר באש תשרופו? v'hanosar ba'eish tisrofu? Why does
it again say והנותר ממנו עד בוקר? v'hanosar mimenu ad boker? Why
does it say a second time, what's left over in the morning?
So מה תלמוד לומר עד בוקר? ma talmud lomar ad boker? Why
does it say עד בוקר ad boker a second time? בא הכתוב
ליתן לו בוקר שני לשריפתו, ba haksav littein lo boker sheini l'sreifaso,
to tell you that if you leave over from the קרבן פסח,
korban pesach, you don't burn it the morning of the 15th, you
burn it the morning of the 16th. So the way the חז"ל
Chazal read the פסוק pasuk is
לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר, lo sosiru mimenu ad boker, don't leave
over from the קרבן פסח korban pesach till the morning of the
15th, והנותר ממנו, v'hanosar mimenu, anything you left over from it, עד
בוקר באש תשרופו, ad boker ba'eish tisrofu, the morning of the 16th
you burn it, which is a, which is a דוחק dochak read
in the פסוק, pasuk, but that's what they read. So what does
it teach you? It teaches you even something that's a מצוה, mitzvah,
what's a מצוה? mitzvah? Burning נותר, nosar, you don't do on the
15th, because the 15th of ניסן Nissan is
פסח Pesach and יום טוב.
Yom Tov. You don't do, you don't violate יום טוב Yom Tov
to do this מצוה mitzvah because it doesn't have to be done
today. It's not specific to today. It could be done tomorrow. So
similarly, a ברית מילה, bris milah, this now gets back to Rav
Safra, which is not an eighth day ברית מילה bris milah and
doesn't have the urgency and the immediacy of being done today. So
you do it on a different day. It doesn't override יום טוב
Yom Tov even if it's a מצוה. mitzvah. אביי אמר קרא, Abaye
amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says, עולת שבת בשבתו, olas Shabbos b'shabbaso,
an עולת שבת olas Shabbos is brought on its שבת, Shabbos, ולא
עולת חול בשבת. v'lo olas chol b'shabbos. If yesterday's עולה, olah, Friday's
עולה, olah, you can't finish it up on שבת, Shabbos, like finish
the burning of the fats, ולא עולת חול ביום טוב. v'lo olas
chol b'Yom Tov. Not only that, you can't burn the fats of
a קרבן korban from ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So same point. Why not? It's a מצוה, mitzvah,
so maybe that should override יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the point
is no, since it's not a מצוה mitzvah of today, here it
can't even really, you know, might not even be able to wait
depending on, anyway, but the point is as long as it's not
today's מצוה mitzvah specifically today's, you don't do it on יום טוב
Yom Tov even though it's a מצוה. mitzvah. רבא אמר קרא, Rava
amar kra, Rava says the פסוק pasuk says הוא לבדו יעשה לכם,
hu levado yei'aseh lachem, it alone, things for the sake of eating,
can be done on יום טוב. Yom Tov. הוא ולא ולא
מכשירין. hu v'lo v'lo machshirin. So first it's a little דרשה drasha
again sort of like a רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer idea. רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer says you can do מכשירי מצוה machshirei mitzvah on שבת.
Shabbos. There's another idea which we'll get to when we learn ביצה
Beitzah or whatever, that you can do מכשירי אוכל נפש machshirei ochel
nefesh on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Can you go out and I
don't know, sharpen your knives or, you know, on יום טוב Yom
Tov things that are preparatory to the actually making of the food
itself? Okay, now to some degree you can because what can you
do on יום טוב Yom Tov besides just putting שחיטה, shech, which
is at least working with the food, it's not directly cooking the
food. Not only that, you know what else you can do? You
can make a fire, right. So at what stage is something called
a מכשירי אוכל נפש? machshirei ochel nefesh? How far back does it
have to be that it's not called cooking but called preparatory to
making the food? You know, should you build an oven if you
need to make an oven to make your food? Okay, so there's
that position that you could do the same way there's a position
of רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer you could do מכשירי מצוה machshirei mitzvah
on שבת, Shabbos, there's a position you could do מכשירי אוכל נפש
machshirei ochel nefesh on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But the גמרא Gemara
says here the דרשה drasha is no, it alone, only things for
food, ולא מכשירין v'lo machshirin and not the things that are preparatory
to the
food. לבדו ולא מילה שלא בזמנה, levado v'lo milah shelo bizmanah, only
food, not מילה שלא בזמנה, milah shelo bizmanah, which is, okay, how
you read that in the פסוק לבדו, pasuk levado, obviously you're coming
with a, you know, with an assumption that you that we have
to clarify the מילה milah and therefore we read that the פסוק
pasuk is emphasizing only food, not a מילה milah that is not
the eighth day. Now, דאתיא מקל וחומר, d'asya mikal vachomer, why did
you need the פסוק pasuk to tell me that? Because you could
have made a קל וחומר kal vachomer argument that you do מילה
שלא בזמנה milah shelo bizmanah on יום טוב. Yom Tov. What's the
קל וחומר kal vachomer argument? You'll remember that from yesterday, right? צרעת
tzara'as trumps עבודה, avodah, עבודה avodah trumps שבת, Shabbos, מילה milah trumps
צרעת, tzara'as, so maybe מילה milah should trump שבת Shabbos or יום
טוב Yom Tov even שלא בזמנה. shelo bizmanah. Anyway, so he has
a specific פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so anyway we have various פסוקים psukim
that all of them tell me that even though יום טוב Yom
Tov is not as weighty as שבת, Shabbos, it's weighty enough to
say don't do a non-eighth day מילה, milah, only מצוות mitzvos of
יום טוב Yom Tov can be done, you know, that need to
be done today can be done today, that are today's מצוה. mitzvah.
Now the גמרא Gemara says
where were
we? רב אשי אמר שבתון עשה הוא. Rav Ashi amar shabbason asei
hu. Now we get back to another, to a more general point.
No, no, no, you don't need any special פסוק. pasuk. Because on
יום טוב Yom Tov the מצוה mitzvah not to do מלאכה melachah
is not only a לא תעשה lo sa'asei of לא תעשה מלאכה,
lo sa'asei melachah, there's a positive. positive מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. It should
be a day of rest, which is a positive מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*
that prevents מלאכה melacha. *melacha*. והוי ליה יום טוב עשה ולא תעשה
*Vahavei lei Yom Tov asei v'lo ta'aseh*. So once you've got that,
there's no reason מילה milah, *milah* should override like תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*
said. פשיטא *Pshita*, right? Once you've got it's a positive and a
negative, then ואין עשה דוחה לא תעשה ועשה *v'ein asei docheh lo
ta'aseh v'asei*. The positive מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of מילה milah *milah* doesn't
override the positive and negative of יום טוב *Yom Tov*. עשה דמילה
*Asei d'milah* is different. עשה *Asei*, we have specific פסוקים *psukim* that
say עשה דמילה *asei d'milah*, which we learned yesterday, overrides שבת Shabbos,
*Shabbos*, and therefore overrides יום טוב *Yom Tov*. But those were פסוקים
*psukim* specifically about מילה milah בזמנה *milah bizmanah*. Once you don't have
those פסוקים *psukim*, so then מילה milah? *milah* becomes like any other
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, you know? And like any other מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*,
why should it override יום טוב *Yom Tov*? It's a positive מצוה
Mitzvah, *mitzvah*, but יום טוב *Yom Tov* is a positive and a
negative. So therefore, if מילה milah. *milah* loses the weight of עשה
דמילה *asei d'milah*, it's just like any other מצוה Mitzvah. *mitzvah*, and
any other מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*, an עשה *asei* does not override an
עשה ולא תעשה *asei v'lo ta'aseh*. Yes, Josh?
Yes, another example of an עשה *asei* associated with יום טוב *Yom
Tov* is the requirement to bring an עולה וחגיגה *olah v'chagigah*.
Yeah, but that's not confronting this מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*. When we say
it goes up against an עשה ולא תעשה *asei v'lo ta'aseh*, it
means doing this מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah* would lead to a violation of,
you know, the עשה ולא תעשה *asei v'lo ta'aseh* of יום טוב
*Yom Tov*. We don't just mean that there happens to be an
עשה *asei* somewhere in the, you know, in the פרשה parsha *parsha*.
Okay? Okay. All right. So let's take a look now as the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wraps up. So therefore, שלא בזמנה *shelo bizmanah* doesn't
override not only שבת Shabbos? *Shabbos*, but not even יום טוב *Yom
Tov*. כלל אמר רבי עקיבא *Klall amar Rabbi Akiva*. By the way,
since we're talking about this, I'll just make a tiny little mention
because it is interesting. A lot of people are not aware that
an, it's very common nowadays, c-sections,
that a c-section is not an עשה דמילה *asei d'milah* of a
c-section does not override שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. Oh, yeah. And that's like
a small little הלכה *halacha* which is extremely relevant, you know, 'cause
some people might not even tell the rabbi or whatever and they
schedule the ברית מילה Bris Milah *bris milah* on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*,
and you know, and sometimes the rabbi doesn't even know. So it's
because the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* learns it out from the פסוק Pasuk
*pasuk*, because it says the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* that we've been darshening
about that overrides שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, ביום השמיני *bayom hashmini*, ביום אפילו
בשבת *bayom afilu b'Shabbos*. So that's in פרשת תזריע *Parshat Tazria*. It
says אשה כי תזריע וילדה זכר *ishah ki tazria v'yaldah zachar*, right?
וביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו *u'bayom hashmini yimol b'sar arlato*, that the
דרש *drash* is כי תזריע במקום שמזרעת *ki tazria b'makom shemazra'at*. When
the birth is through the place that normally, you know, sort of
like conception happens. So therefore, when it comes, so the דרש *drash*
is that when it's a breech baby, not breech, excuse me, when
it's a cesarean section, it's not in that פרשה *parsha*. That's not
a דרש *drash* here, but it's worth noting because it's a big
exception to the rule of ברית מילה Bris Milah *bris milah*. Once
we're saying this, I should also say that there's an interesting opinion,
although it's much harder, not much harder, the first thing is a
straight גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that we pasken. But there's some people wonder
and speculate that if it is an artificial insemination, עשה *asei*, should
it be דוחה שבת Shabbos. *docheh Shabbos*? Now there, there's no גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* that says not, but there are some people that ask
the question that maybe it doesn't because maybe this is an emphasis
on like totally natural birth or something. But that's a, you know,
that's a position that doesn't have much to back it up, but
there are people that raise that question. But it is really important
to know the idea that a c-section is not דוחה *docheh*, a
c-section עשה דמילה *asei d'milah* is not דוחה שבת Shabbos. *docheh Shabbos*.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. כלל אמר רבי עקיבא
*Klall amar Rabbi Akiva*. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב הלכה כרבי עקיבא
*Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav: Halacha k'Rabbi Akiva*. The ruling is like
Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Akiva basically rejects רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rabbi Eliezer*
and he says if it could have been done yesterday, you don't
do it today. ותנן נמי גבי פסח Pesach *U'tenan nami gabei Pesach*.
כהאי גוונא *K'hai gavna*, we taught similarly by פסח Pesach *Pesach*. כלל
אמר רבי עקיבא *Klall amar Rabbi Akiva*. Even though פסח Pesach. *Pesach*
is דוחה שבת Shabbos *docheh Shabbos*, anything that in theory could have
been taken care of earlier, כל מלאכה שאפשר לעשותה מערב שבת Shabbos.
אינה דוחה את השבת *Kol melacha she'efshar la'asotah m'erev Shabbos einah dochah
et haShabbos*. Anything that could have been done for the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach *korban Pesach* before שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* cannot override. And that
means in theory, like it's not just like, you know, I didn't
get my knife back from the store until שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* or
whatever. You know, in theory, anything that could have been taken care
of before שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* does not get to be done on
שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. Only the thing that absolutely must be done on
שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, like the שחיטה shechitah *shechitah*. שחיטה שאי אפשר לעשותה
מערב שבת Shabbos, *Shechitah she'i efshar la'asotah m'erev Shabbos*, שחיטה *shechitah* you
can't do on the 13th, you have to do on the 14th,
so דוחה את השבת *dochah et haShabbos*, that you do on שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos*. Okay. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב הלכה כרבי עקיבא *V'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav: Halacha k'Rabbi Akiva*. And רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*
also said like רב *Rav* over there, we rule like רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva*. וצריכא *U'tzricha*.
Now he had to tell me we rule like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* in both cases 'cause I couldn't have inferred one from the
other. די אשמעינן גבי מילה milah *De'ishmi'inan gabei milah*, if you'd just
told me we rule like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* by מילה milah
*milah*, התם הוא דמכשירין אפשר לעשות מערב שבת Shabbos. לא דחי שבת
Shabbos. *hatam hu de'machshirin efshar la'asot m'erev Shabbos lo dachi Shabbos*. There
I understand why if you could have done preparatory stuff before שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos* it doesn't override שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, דליכא כרת Kares, *de'leika
kares*, because
right
because there's no כרת Kares *kares* immediately, meaning there'll be כרת Kares,
*kares* maybe when he grows up, but not doing it on the
eighth day doesn't translate into כרת kares. *kares*. So there I would
say fine, if you didn't take care of that stuff you wait
till Sunday. אבל פסח Pesach דאיכא כרת kares *Aval Pesach de'ika kares*,
by פסח Pesach *Pesach* where there is כרת kares? *kares*, אימא *eima*,
if you don't bring פסח Pesach *Pesach* today you כרת. kares? So
אימא לדחו, Aima lidchu, maybe it'll be put, maybe, maybe even the
מכשירין Machshirin should push off. Okay, now of course it's a little
funny, you always have פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, but whatever. Anyway, פסח
Pesach where there's more of an immediate sense of כרת, kares maybe
I would allow even the מכשירין. Machshirin. Says no, by פסח we
even, we don't allow the מכשירין Machshirin by פסח. That has to
get taken care of beforehand. Now, אימא לדחו שבת, Aima lidchu Shabbos,
maybe
it'll push off שבת, Shabbat. he tells me no. ואשמיעינן גבי פסח,
V'ashmi'inan gabei Pesach, if you said by פסח you don't do the
מכשירין Machshirin משום דלא נכרתו עליה י"ג בריתות, mishum d'lo nichretu aleha
yud-gimmel britot, because פסח although it's כרת kares and although it's a
sense of like the covenant, you know, it's sort of the whole
foundational event of the Jewish people, nevertheless doesn't say thirteen times 'This
is my covenant'. אבל מילה דנכרתו עליה י"ג בריתות Aval milah d'nichretu
aleha yud-gimmel britos and in the פרשה of ברית מילה Bris Milah
with אברהם, Avraham, thirteen times it emphasizes that this is my covenant.
So therefore that is so weighty, even more weighty than the immediate
sense of כרת, kares אימא לדחו שבת, Aima lidchu Shabbos, maybe it'll
even the מכשירין Machshirin will override שבת? Shabbat צריכא, Tzricha, so it
has to tell me no, I'm sorry, the act itself overrides שבת
Shabbat but things that in theory could have been done before they
do not. And if you didn't do them, then you'll have to
do it on Sunday, or for פסח you'll have to wait till
the פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. And that's how we rule against רבי
אליעזר. Okay, so that is the idea that eighth day ברית מילה
Bris Milah overrides שבת, Shabbat. not the מכשירין, Machshirin, and I gave
you an interesting, the interesting and important exception of what do you
call it, of a
C-section. Okay, now the משנה Mishnah moves on about what can be
done on שבת Shabbat itself. עושין כל צרכי מילה בשבת, Osin kol
tzorchei milah beShabbos, you do anything you need to do for the
ברית מילה Bris Milah on שבת. Shabbat Now this really is going
to fall into two categories. One are things which are part of
the מצוה Mitzvah of ברית מילה Bris Milah, because ברית מילה Bris
Milah. overrides שבת. Shabbat And the other are health-related issues because of
פיקוח נפש. Pikuach Nefesh. So even when you're done with the ברית
מילה, Bris Milah, you can do health-related issues on שבת Shabbat. as
well, that's the פיקוח נפש Pikuach Nefesh category. So let's take a
look.
מוהלין ופורעין ומוצצין, Molin u'porin u'motzatzin, you can do the מילה, milah
cut away the foreskin, you can do the פריעה, priah, which is
tearing away the
membrane, the thin membrane that's under the foreskin, that's also part of
the ברית מילה. bris milah. ומוצצין, U'motzatzin, you can suck out the
blood from the point of the incision. We all know about מציצה
בפה, Metzitzah b'peh, I'll talk about that in a little bit. ונותנין
עליה אספלנית, Venotenin aleha isplanit, you can put on it a bandage.
Now, now we're moving into the health issues, maybe the ומוצצין motzatzin
as well, as we'll see. וכמון, U'kamon, and cumin, which would seem
to be some type of a health-related, you know, thing for the
wound. ואם לא שחק מערב שבת, Ve'im lo shachak m'erev Shabbos, now
if you didn't grind this כמון cumin from ערב שבת, erev Shabbos,
לועס בשיניו, loeis b'shinav, you would chew it in your teeth ונותן,
venoten, and put it then on the wound. אם לא טרף יין
ושמן מערב שבת, Im lo taraf yayin vashemen m'erev Shabbos, now apparently
what they would also do would be putting some mixture of oil
and wine on the wound, if you did not mix them together
on ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, נותן זה בפני עצמו וזה בפני עצמו,
noten zeh bifnei atzmo v'zeh bifnei atzmo, don't mix them together now,
put each one on separately. Not exactly clear what the problem would
be about mixing wine and oil even on שבת. Shabbat But anyway,
we try to do this with a שינוי shinui if you did
not prepare it ahead of time. ואין עושין לה חלוק לכתחילה, Ve'ein
osin lah chaluk lechatchilah, you cannot make literally like a garment, but
what it actually means is that they would put a type of
a, of, of like
a wrap, not just around the wound, but around, around, you know,
the the, the, you know, the penis itself. אבל כורך עליה סמרטוט,
Aval korech aleha smartut, but you can wrap around it, not this
special like wrap maybe which was cut to size or so on,
but you can take some type of a cloth and wrap it
around. אם לא התקין מערב שבת, Im lo hitkin m'erev Shabbos, now
if you did not prepare it ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, meaning you
didn't even have it at the place where there's going to be
the ברית מילה, bris milah. כורך על אצבעו, korech al etzbao, you
can wrap it around your finger ומביא, umeivi, and bring it ואפילו
מחצר אחרת, ve'afilu mechatzar acheret, even from another courtyard. Now putting things
on your body doesn't stop it from being carried. You can carry
on your body, not just on your hand, but it is a
שינוי, shinui, you know, if you wrap it around, it's not the
normal way you carry something. And the other thing to mention is
it says מחצר אחרת, mechatzar acheret, from another courtyard. Another courtyard is
not necessarily a biblical violation, another courtyard could be a rabbinic, you
didn't make an עירוב חצירות, eiruv chatzeiros, but it doesn't mean necessarily
you're going through רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So we'll have to see
about those last cases. Also what exactly is the purpose of this
little חלוק? chaluk? רש"י Rashi says the purpose is not necessarily health
like the bandage before, the purpose is that somehow so that the
מילה milah doesn't reverse itself, so the skin doesn't somehow move back
and cover back and cover back up. So it's part of the
מילה milah more than it's part of a health issue. Anyway, the
certainly the emphasis at the bottom of the משנה Mishnah is that
you need to do a שינוי. shinui. So I turn your attention,
we have to turn the page anyway, so as you turn the
page look at the little
תוספות Tosafos on קל"ג ע"ב Kuf Lamed Gimmel Amud Bais where it
says there לועס בשיניו, loeis b'shinav, you chew it with your teeth,
this כמון. cumin. So תוספות says אף על גב דאחר מילה חולה
שיש בו סכנה הוא, af al gav d'achar milah choleh sheyesh bo
sakanah hu, even though he's a חולה choleh that there's a, you
know, life threat to him, so why do you, so what, so
why do you have to chew with your teeth? בכל מקום כמה
דאפשר לשנויי משנינן. Bechol makom kama d'efshar l'shannuyei meshanninan. We as much
as you can do it in an unusual way you do it.
Now that raises general questions about חולה. choleh. Do we say when
somebody's really חולה שיש בו סכנה choleh she-yesh bo sakono and you're
really engaged in life saving behavior, you have to try to do
things with a שינוי? shinuy? That's normally not what we say. So
you know, it gets to like this grey area similar to the
case that we had before about a woman in childbirth where the
status is חולה שיש בו סכנה. choleh she-yesh bo sakono. On the
other hand, you know, does it mean that there it's the same
real חולה שיש בו סכנה choleh she-yesh bo sakono as somebody that,
you know, has had a building fall on them, you know, or
is having a heart attack? And, you know, and are these things
like really like, so I think that it—so I think that it's
interesting, I'm not obviously giving a פסק psak here, but the two
places so far we've seen of an indication of do things with
a שינוי shinuy is a woman in childbirth and the baby after
the ברית מילה. bris milah. Where I think that a normal person
would have said unless it's a special case, I'm not going to
say that this person is יש בו סכנה, yesh bo sakono, meaning
sometimes they could be יש בו סכנה, yesh bo sakono, right, but
maybe not in like a—not like that that's the standard label we
put on it. So both of these, the חידוש chidush is—the first
חידוש chidush is that we—that we just automatically treat them as חולה
שיש בו סכנה choleh she-yesh bo sakono even without any special indicators
that there's a, you know, that there's some particular high risk in
this case. Then once we say that, we also say, okay, but
then try to do some שינוי shinuy if you're doing things, you
know, if you're doing מלאכה. It's a different type of an approach
than somebody that's like, you know, clearly a חולה שיש בו סכנה
choleh she-yesh bo sakono based on the circumstances of the case. So
it's just worth noting that it's in these—so far we've seen a
שינוי shinuy that but it's in these two cases and it's not
the general approach to a real חולה שיש בו סכנה. choleh she-yesh
bo sakono. Okay, so let's take a look now as the גמרא
Gemara deals with these various parts of the ברית מילה. bris milah,
Top of קל"ג עמוד ב'. kuf-lamed-gimmel amud beis.
מכדי, Michdi, says the גמרא, Gemara let's take a look. תני כולהו,
Tani kulehu,
we already said all the things you can do. You can put
on cumin, you can do all—you can do whatever, כל צרכי מילה.
kol tzorchei milah. So, you know, we gave a lot of specifics.
כל צרכי מילה לאתויי מאי? Kol tzorchei milah l'asuyei mai? What's the
point of him saying everything you need? What else are we saying
that we haven't mentioned? Now maybe in terms of health issues there's
a million things we could list. But—but we're not yet up to
the health issues. We're up to the act of the ברית מילה.
Bris Milah. So we say you cut away the skin, you cut
away the membrane. So—so what do you have to say all things
of the מילה? milah That is all things of the מילה. milah,
What isn't mentioned? So the גמרא Gemara says לאתויי הא דתנו רבנן,
l'asuyei ha d'tanu rabanan, that which our rabbis taught: המל, Hamal, somebody
who is doing the ברית מילה, Bris Milah כל זמן שהוא עוסק
במילה, kol zman she-hu osek b'milah, as long as he's in the
middle of the act, like he's there in the cutting, so חוזר
בין על ציצין המעכבין את המילה בין על ציצין שאין מעכבין את
המילה. chozer bein al tzitzin h'me'akvin es h'milah bein al tzitzin she-ein
me'akvin es h'milah. You can go back—I mean you're not really go
back 'cause you're still in the process—but you can even if all
you have left are ציצין tzitzin are like little strands of skin.
So you can if you left over little strands of skin, sometimes
they prevent the מילה Milah from being considered acceptable, and sometimes they
don't, depends how much they cover up the, you know, the—cornea, it's
not cornea, what's the ridge called? In Hebrew it's called the עטרה.
atarah. What?
Corona would know.
Corona would know. Anyway, that ridge that's near the top of—what? Corona?
Okay, right, corona. I was saying cornea which is part of the
eye. Okay, corona. Anyway, so if that ridge, the majority of it
is still covered up, then the מילה Milah, is no good. So
if you have a little of it covered up, that would be
a ציץ שאינו מעכב, tzitz she-eino me'akev, a little piece of skin
that is not מעכב. me'akev. If you have too much of it
covered up, it's מעכב. me'akev. So while you're still in the middle
of the process, you can go back and finish cutting away all
the skin, whether it is for little pieces that prevent it from
being good or even if it—even if it's כשר kosher but it's
not complete, so you can finish cutting away those pieces of skin.
Okay, כל הציצין שאין—so kol ha-tzitzin she-ein that's while you're involved in
it. פירש, Peireish, once you have separated, you like put down your
knife, you know, you thought you're done and then you go back
and you look and you see oh my gosh, there's something I
didn't finish up. Then על ציצין המעכבין את המילה חוזר, al tzitzin
h'me'akvin es h'milah chozer, you can go back if the מילה Milah
still isn't good, if there's things that prevent it from being good.
If most of it is
covered—this corona. אבל על ציצין שאין מעכבין את המילה אינו חוזר, aval
al tzitzin she-ein me'akvin es h'milah eino chozer, you cannot go back.
So the חידוש chidush of כל צרכי מילה kol tzorchei milah is
that as long as you're still involved in the act, you can
do things that even though the מילה Milah is already כשר, kosher,
you have now cut away enough that the מילה milah is כשר,
kosher, you were יוצא yotzei the מצוה Mitzvah. as—but the חידוש chidush
is that since you're still have are involved in the act, you
can continue to cutting away the rest 'cause it's all considered part
of the act of מילה Milah. even though were you to stop
right now, you would be יוצא. yotzei. Okay, so even though it's
not—it's not like the need to do the מצוה Mitzvah is overriding
because the מצוה Mitzvah is done, since it's still part of the
act of מילה, milah. that can be done as well. So that's
the חידוש chidush of כל צרכי מילה. kol tzorchei milah. So the
גמרא Gemara says, which is a חידוש, chidush, מאי דהוה סלקא דעתך,
mai d'hava salka daitach, once you're done with the מצוה, Mitzvah you
can—you have to stop. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
מאן תנא פירש אינו חוזר, man tanna peireish eino chozer, who's the
תנא tanna that would say now so— So the חידוש Chidush is
that when you're not פירש Peireish you can still keep on going,
but the גמרא Gemara says maybe even after you separate you can
go back, it's still all part of the מילה even after you
stopped. So who is the one that says that once you stopped
you cannot go back as long as once if you were יוצא?
Yotzei? So אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabba
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקה הוא, Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka hu,
it's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael the son of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka he, דתניא detanya we learned in a ברייתא,
Braisa, ארבעה עשר שחל להיות בשבת, Arba'ah Asar she-chal lihyos be-Shabbos, the
14th of ניסן Nisan is on שבת, Shabbat, so you're bringing the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on שבת. Shabbos? How much can you do
on שבת Shabbos. after it's been slaughtered? So מפשיט את הפסח עד
החזה, mafshit es ha-Pesach ad ha-chaze, so you're hanging the פסח from
its legs, okay, so you're going from the legs towards the head,
you're hanging it from its legs so you can skin it until
you get to the chest. Once you get to the chest area
or you uncover the chest area then you cut it open and
you take out the innards, you take out the אימורים Amurim and
you burn the אימורים. Amurim. So the reason we let you on
שבת Shabbos skin it till the chest area is because on שבת
Shabbos. you have to burn the אימורים, Amurim, it has to be
done today and this is part of getting to the אימורים Amurim
in a way that doesn't make it messy because you don't want
to cut through the skin, you want to flay it first and
then
cut straight into the body. דברי רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקה, Divrei Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, that's
what he said. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, the sages say, מפשיטין את
כולו, mafshitin es kulo, you can actually do the whole thing, okay,
because part of the reason is that
it helps preserve the meat that you're going to eat that night.
ורבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה V'Rabbi Yishmael beno shel
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka says what do I care about tonight? Today
is today, the only thing you can do are things for שבת,
Shabbos: so once you get to the chest you have to stop.
Now the גמרא Gemara understands according to him, look, I get that
what you did is you flayed it to the chest, you cut
into it, you took out the אימורים, Amurim, but now and that
was allowed because of שבת Shabbos and it's part of the קרבן
Korban on שבת. Shabbos? Now why can't you go back and finish?
Why don't we just say, okay, it's finishing the process, the process
was allowed, this is the end of the process? So that seems
parallel to our idea of ברית מילה. Bris milah, You were יוצא
Yotzei the מצוה, Mitzvah. once you stopped and pulled back you can't
re-engage, it's not considered part of the same process, it's considered a
new act, and a new act does not have a license here
to violate שבת. Shabbos So there's a nice parallel between these two
cases. So that seems very nice, so the גמרא Gemara is going
to say ממה, Mima, maybe they're not exactly the same. עד כאן
לא קאמר רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה התם, Ad
kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka hasam,
over there he said you can't go back and re-engage after you've
taken out the אימורים, Amurim, משום דלא בעינן זה אלי ואנוהו, mishum
d'lo ba'inan Zeh Eli v'anvehu, because it's not an idea of like
beautifying a מצוה. mitzvah Okay, by finishing to skin the thing, you
know, that's not the part that's going on the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, so
there's no מצוה mitzvah, that's being beautified. אבל הכא דבעינן זה אלי
ואנוהו, Aval hacha d'ba'inan Zeh Eli v'anvehu,
here where you're doing the מצוה of מילה, so by going back
and finishing it you're making it more, you know, aesthetic. הכא נמי,
Hacha nami, so maybe that would be allowed. דתניא, Detanya, we learned
in a ברייתא, Braisa, זה אלי ואנוהו, Zeh Eli v'anvehu, this you
know is my God and I will glorify him, so what does
that mean? התנאה לפניו במצוות, Hitna'eh lefanav be-mitzvos, beautify yourself in front
of God with מצוות. Mitzvos. עשה לפניו סוכה נאה ולולב נאה ושופר
נאה וציצית נאה וספר תורה נאה, Aseh lefanav sukkah na'ah v'lulav na'ah
v'shofar na'ah v'tzitzis na'ah v'sefer Torah na'eh,
make a beautiful סוכה, Sukkah, לולב, Lulav, שופר, Shofar, ציצית, Tzitzis, ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah, וכתבו לשמו, v'chasvo lishmo,
when you're writing the ספר תורה Sefer Torah it should be with
intent of God's name, that's probably the emphasis on זה אלי, Zeh
Eli, right, there God is very much the center, בדיו נאה ובקולמוס
נאה ובלבלר אומן, bedyo na'eh u-bekulmus na'eh u-velavlar uman, beautiful ink, a
nice you know pen, quill, with an expert scribe, וכרכו בשיראין נאה,
ve-keracho beshira'in na'eh,
wrap it with beautiful like you know silks and cloths, even though
the מצוה object itself is not being beautified, but you're beautifying the
stuff around it so it's beautifying it, you know, even though, so
making it beautiful by what you accompany it with. All this is
a מצוה of the idea of beautifying the מצוה. So we're going
to continue in this in a minute, but the immediate point is
that you know by the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach it's not that
the meat is more beautiful, first of all, you know, do you
call the meat of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach a מצוה object
the same way you call these things a מצוה object? You might
have asked the same question, do you call the ברית מילה Bris
milah, a מצוה object? It's like part of your body. But I
think the other bigger point is that in one case the flaying
is not beautifying the meat. Going back here and finishing the job
is making it more aesthetic, you know, so therefore maybe even if
you separate you're allowed to re-engage even on שבת Shabbos because it's
automatically defined as more part of the מילה because it makes the
מילה more aesthetic as opposed to re-engaging by the קרבן פסח korban
pesach where it's not considered once you separated it's not considered part
of the same act. So that seemed to be the point. It
is actually interesting that I recently read an article that said you
know I normally have always read this פסוק of the רבניק דרשא
rabbinic drasha of התנאה לפניו במצוות Hitna'eh lefanav be-mitzvos which was basically
meaning
make... The grammar is glorify yourself with מצוות, mitzvos, beautify yourself and
actually the original grammar was even more like that. I forget the
anyway whatever. Which פסוק?
זה אלי ואנוהו. zeh eli ve'anvehu. But the rabbinic דרשה drasha is
not be
glorify the מצוות, mitzvos, it's התנאה לפניו, hitnaeh lefanav,
glorify yourself in God's presence through the מצוות. mitzvos. So anyway I
recently read an article that says that the original דרשה drasha was
not so much about glorifying the מצוות, mitzvos, but that seeing the
idea that when you're doing the מצווה, mitzvah, that's like a way
in which you ornament yourself. The same way you put on jewelry
for God, your jewelry is the מצווה. mitzvah. So you're glorifying yourself
in presence of God. And that ואנוהו anvehu is yourself as a
זה אלי zeh eli that that might actually be almost like a
צלם אלוהים tzelem elohim type of an idea, you know, the emphasis
of of that. So it's an interesting little twist on this. It's
not a straight point of beautify the מצוות. mitzvos. Beautify yourself, you
know, through the מצוות. mitzvos. Anyway, the point though being that maybe
by מילה we have more license to go back and it's more
seen as part of the מצווה mitzvah even after you separate because
of the זה אלי ואנוהו zeh eli ve'anvehu idea. Now the גמרא
Gemara finishes this דרשה drasha of זה אלי ואנוהו zeh eli ve'anvehu
in the following way. אבא שאול אומר, Abba Shaul omer, אבא שאול
Abba Shaul says, ואנוהו הוי דומה לו. ve'anvehu hevei domeh lo. Glorify
him means be like God. Okay, some read this as אני והוא
ani ve'hu like, you know, I and He, God. Okay, so how
and this is the principle of, you know, imitatio dei, the obligation
to like והלכת בדרכיו vehalachta bidrachav of try of striving to be
godlike. So what does that mean? מה הוא חנון ורחום אף אתה
היה חנון ורחום. mah hu chanun verachum af atah heyei chanun verachum.
The same way he is compassionate and, you know, and gracious, you
also be gracious and compassionate. I'll also say one word about this
as well, there's two very different דרשות drashot of the
of the והלכת בדרכיו vehalachta bidrachav or
הוי דומה לו. hevei domeh lo. One is focuses on character traits,
רחום וחנון. rachum vechanun. The other focuses on actions. מה הוא מלביש
ערומים אף אתה מלביש ערומים. mah hu malbish arumim af atah malbish
arumim. מה הוא מכניס אורחים אף אתה מכניס אורחים. mah hu machnis
orchim af atah machnis orchim. The same way God clothed the naked
and well, you know, and visits the sick, you should clothe the
naked and visit the sick. So actually it points to, you know,
two different types of of of
morality. There's, I forget the phrase, but there's one type of a
thing which is very much focused on the action. And then there's
this other one which is there are technical terms for this, like
in, you know, in moral philosophy. About about one sense of morality
which basically focuses on doing good actions and the other which focuses
on ultimately like, you know, emphasizing the character traits. Doing, you know,
so it's not so much about what you do, it's about the
character traits that you cultivate within yourself. רמב"ם Rambam actually was on
the tip of my tongue it fell off. Anyway,
רמב"ם Rambam was a very big proponent of the character traits, interestingly,
not about the pragmatic good that the actions do or following a
moral code, but of developing the character traits. For example, רמב"ם Rambam
says this מצווה mitzvah of of the מצווה mitzvah of learning פרקי
אבות Pirkei Avot that says
you know that
it's not לפי המעשה, lefi hamaaseh, it's not לפי גודל המעשה, lefi
godel hamaaseh, הכל לפי המעשה ולא לפי גודל המעשה. hakol lefi hamaaseh
velo lefi godel hamaaseh. It's all by the action and not by
the size of the action or something like that. So the רמב"ם
Rambam says what does that mean? So the רמב"ם Rambam says well,
what it means is it's more important to give צדקה tzedakah a
dollar a time for a hundred times than to write a one
hundred dollar check. Why? Because if you give a dollar a time
for a hundred times, you more cultivate in yourself this attribute of
generosity and compassion and so on. So it's actually interesting so רמב"ם
Rambam was very much focused on that aspect of morality, and it's
actually interesting because the רמב"ם Rambam says fitting in with his whole
issue about, you know, this sense that we can't really know God
and describe God and it's a negative theology. We only can say
what God is not. So then he says so why did חז"ל
Chazal why did the תורה Torah constantly use these terms to describe
God? חנון, רחום chanun, rachum and so on. So he says the
only reason the תורה Torah used those terms in describing God was
so we should know what character traits we should emulate. It's for
the purpose of this idea of והלכת בדרכיו vehalachta bidrachav and being
like God. So the תורה Torah emphasizes these ways because you could
describe God in many ways, maybe some ways, you know, even not
so complimentary ones you say God makes hurricanes, you know, it takes
life, life. So no, this is to tell us how we're supposed
to characterize God so that we can also think about that as
what we're supposed to strive for. So anyway all of these things
רמב"ם Rambam's theology and his moral philosophy all sort of tie together
with this emphasis on character traits, which is what this גמרא Gemara
is saying as opposed to a different type of an approach of
זה אלי ואנוהו zeh eli ve'anvehu which focuses on action. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues and says the following. אלא אמר רב
אשי. Ella amar Rav Ashi. So that was a nice little
digression. Who is the one that says you can't go back? Maybe
here you should be able to go back for the reason we
just said of זה אלי ואנוהו. Zeh Eli v'anveihu. So rather, says
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, הא מני רבי יוסי? Ha mani Rabbi Yose?
It's רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. דתנן: De'tnan: בין שנראה בעליל ובין שלא
נראה בעליל מחללין עליו את השבת. Bein shenira ba'alil ubein shelo nira
ba'alil, mechalalin alav et Hashabbat.
Whether you saw the new moon clearly or not clearly, you can
violate שבת Shabbos? to go to the בית דין Beis Din to
testify, even if you saw clearly, even if you could assume other
people saw it. רבי יוסי אומר: Rabbi Yose omer: נראה בעליל אין
מחללין עליו את השבת. Nira ba'alil ein mechalalin alav et Hashabbat. If
it was seen clearly you cannot violate שבת. Shabbos. So this is
a very weak analogy. The גמרא Gemara is saying the same way
there he won't let you violate שבת Shabbos. if it's not necessary
because other people saw it, here too, you won't violate שבת Shabbos
if it's not necessary if you've already finished and what's left does
not prevent the מצוה. So the גמרא Gemara says: you can't compare
those. מנאי? Minai? Why do you think those are comparable? דילמא עד
כאן לא קאמר רבי יוסי התם דלא ניתן שבת לידחות. Dilma ad
kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yose hatam de'lo niten Shabbat lidachot. Over there,
there's no license to violate שבת. Shabbos. If other people saw it,
you don't have a license... you can assume other people saw it,
you have no license to violate שבת Shabbos. for you. אבל הכא
דניתן שבת לידחות, Aval hacha de'niten Shabbat lidachot, here where there was
a license to violate שבת Shabbos and the act you were allowed
to do, so once you were allowed to begin the act, הכא
נמי, Hacha nami, maybe even if you stopped and even if technically
you could be יוצא, Yotzei, since you were allowed to begin the
act, you can go back and that will be considered a continuation
of the act of מילה.
So here maybe we could still argue that you could go back,
and even though the comparison is a nice analogy, you have the
extra idea of זה אלי ואנוהו Zeh Eli v'anveihu here, so maybe
you should be allowed to go back. אלא אמר נהרדעי: Ela amar
Nehardai: רבנן דפליגי עליה דרבי יוסי. Rabbanan de'pligi alei de'Rabbi Yose.
It's another רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and it's actually the רבנן Rabbanan
who argue on רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose in a different case. דתנן,
De'tnan, and this is a very interesting comparison: ארבעה כהנים נכנסים. Arba'ah
Kohanim nichnasim.
When it's שבת Shabbos and you have to switch the לחם הפנים
Lechem haPanim on the שלחן, Shulchan, you have four כהנים Kohanim that
go in to the קודש. Kodesh. שנים בידם שני סדרים, Shnayim beyadam
shnei sedarim, two are carrying
the two columns of bread, one column per person, the new freshly
baked bread that's going to be put on on שבת. Shabbos? ושנים
בידם שני בזיכין, Ushnayim beyadam shnei bazichin,
and two of them are carrying
the two little spoons of incense that would also be on the
table, that would be burned on שבת Shabbos? and then the bread
would be
eaten. וארבעה מקדימים לפניהם, V'arba'ah makdimim lifneihem,
and four people would go in before them. שנים ליטול שני סדרים,
Shnayim litol shnei sedarim,
two to remove the existing two columns. ושנים ליטול שני בזיכין, Ushnayim
litol shnei bazichin, and two to remove the existing two little spoons
of incense, which then the incense would be burned. המכניסים עומדים בצפון.
Hamachnisim omdim batzafon.
Now the מנורה Menorah was
stood in the north and it was faced east to west. So
the new ones would be on the north, which would mean basically
they would be between the מנורה Menorah and the wall. ופניהם לדרום,
Ufneihem ladarom,
facing the south. המוציאים, Hamotzi'im,
those that are taking out the bread, עומדים בדרום, Omdim badarom, maybe
on the south side of the מנורה, Menorah, like their backs would
be towards the center of the היכל. Heichal. ופניהם
לצפון, Ufneihem latzafon,
and
they're facing the north. אלו מושכין
ואלו מניחין. Elu moshchin v'elu manichim. The ones taking it out would
be drawing the bread out as the others would be putting the
bread on. So basically that because it says: לחם פנים לפני תמיד.
Lechem Panim lefanai tamid. Right, the לחם הפנים Lechem haPanim has to
be constantly before, so as they're pulling it out, others are putting
it on exactly at the same time and there's not even a
second where the שלחן Shulchan is without bread. טפח של זה בצד
טפח של זה. Tefach shel zeh b'tzad tefach shel zeh. One person's
טפח Tefach of one is right near the טפח Tefach of the
other, meaning the breads are almost touching, one is being pulled out
as the other is being put in. משום שנאמר לפני תמיד, Mishum
shene'emar lefanai tamid,
because it says before Me constantly. רבי יוסי אומר: Rabbi Yose omer:
אפילו אלו נוטלים ואלו מניחים אף זה תמיד. Afilu elu notlim v'elu
manichim, af zeh tamid.
Even if first one takes it out and then there's a wait
an hour and then the next one puts it in, that's still
considered לפני תמיד. Lefanai tamid. So now we understand what that has
to do with ברית מילה, bris milah don't we? So it seems
completely irrelevant but the גמרא Gemara actually is making a fascinating shift.
It's no longer talking about a principle of overriding שבת, Shabbos it's
talking about a more abstract principle of continuity of action. And what
it's saying is like this: that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose here says
that even if you stop, there's a period where there's no bread
on the table and then you put it on again, we can
see that in some type of sense of continuous. Okay, it was
all there the same day, there was some sense of continuity. The
רבנן Rabbanan say if you want a sense of being continuous then
there can't be a moment's break. And if there was a moment
where the table was without bread, you can't call it תמיד. Tamid.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying by analogy, if I stop doing
the ברית מילה, bris milah, I can't go back because You cannot
consider it a continuous action because the rabbis here say that any
break means that it's not continuous. Now of course you could make
it very—that's very nice as an abstract, sort of a conceptual point,
but you then can make a distinction. There's a big difference between
a static situation and an active
situation. Right, if I say was there bread constantly on the table,
then if there was one minute there wasn't bread, it wasn't constant.
But if I'm looking as an action, I might say that even
with a break, the action, there's a sense of continuity of action
that's different than a continuity of a static state. Okay, so you
could make the distinction, but that's at least what the גמרא Gemara
is saying. What?
Bris is only one person doing it.
Right, so but that's the point that why it's like why it's
an analogy, because there we're really talking about is it considered that
the שולחן Shulchan has bread constantly, not is it one action? And
we're trying to compare the sense of continuity of a state, which
is the case by the שולחן, Shulchan, to continuity of action. And
that's exactly my point. You could have said, okay, if a state
is interrupted, it's not a continuous state, but an action interrupted and
maybe even the same person then re-engages and it's part of the
same process, maybe that should be categorized differently. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara though interestingly does understand that so the bottom line of all
this is that the חידוש chiddush is number one, if you haven't
disengaged, you can continue even if technically you could be considered yourself
done. And B, the גמרא Gemara thinks in theory there might even
be a position that you could re-engage even if you've been יוצא,
yotze, but the opinion of the ברייתא Beraita was you cannot re-engage
here connecting it to this discussion of לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim. Okay,
let's try to finish to the two dots. The גמרא Gemara says
like this, תנו רבנן: Tnu Rabbanan: מחתכין mechatkhin את המילה. et hamila.
You can actually
like finish off, like literally I think from the same word of
like a tweezer, you can finish removing the little
strands of the מילה. ואם לא חתך ענוש כרת. ve'im lo chatach
anush kares. And if you didn't do it, you know, then you
get כרת. kares? So exactly, who gets כרת kares. and for what?
For ברית מילה bris milah or for violating שבת? Shabbos, So the
גמרא Gemara is going to interpret this not as the ברית—let's bris
take a look. מני, mani, who's getting כרת? kares. אמר רב כהנא
אומן. Amar Rav Kahana: Umman. The אומן, Umman, the מוהל. Mohel. Now
why would the מוהל Mohel get כרת? Not for not having a
ברית מילה, bris milah, but he would get כרת for violating שבת.
Shabbos So the way it's reading it is you did the ברית
מילה bris milah, on שבת and you didn't finish it. Then you
get כרת for violating שבת. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
מתקיף לה רב פפא: matkif lah Rav Pappa: אומן? Umman? The אומן?
Umman? לימא להו, leima lehu, why doesn't he say to the other
people even if he didn't finish the שבת: אנא עביד פלגא דמצוה
אתון עבידו פלגא דמצוה. ana avid palga de-mitzvah, atun avid palga de-mitzvah.
Fine, I only did half, you guys finish the
rest. Meaning, it was permissible for me to do the ברית מילה,
bris milah I did half, even if I didn't finish it, what
I did was allowed on שבת and it still could have been
done, somebody else could have done the other half. So therefore why
should I be considered having violated שבת? What I did was permissible.
אלא
אמר רב פפא גדול. Ela Amar Rav Pappa: Gadol. Okay, what it
means is that
the—it means the adult. What does it mean the adult? It means
let me just check רש"י Rashi here,
right, we're not talking about שבת anymore, we're talking it's a weekday,
and you the adult get כרת because you didn't finish your ברית
מילה, bris milah. you still have—you're still לא נמול. lo nimol. So
the גמרא says מתקיף לה רב אשי: matkif lah Rav Ashi: גדול
בהדיא כתיב ביה? gadol behedya ketiv beih? וערל זכר אשר לא ימול.
v'arel zachar asher lo yimmol. So what, that's a חידוש, chiddush, that
if somebody never gets his ברית מילה bris milah done he gets
כרת? The ברייתא Beraita wouldn't have to say that, just say you
didn't—it wasn't a good ברית מילה. bris milah אלא אמר רב אשי.
Ela Amar Rav Ashi. So רב אשי Rav Ashi says לעולם אומן,
le'olam umman, we'll go back to שבת and it's the מוהל Mohel
that gets כרת. Now how could the מוהל Mohel be considered have
violated שבת? You know, he he did half, let somebody else finish
the other half. וכגון דאתא בין השמשות. ukegon de'ata bein hashmashot. He
came right at nightfall, it literally is בין השמשות bein hashmashot to
שבת. ואמרו ליה לא מספקת, ve'amru leih: Lo mesafket, and they said
to him, you don't have enough time to finish the ברית מילה
bris milah before it becomes night and it's, you know, so you
won't get it all done on שבת. So you can't violate שבת
because you're not going to get it done on
שבת. ואמר להו מספקינא. ve'amar lehu: Mesafkina. No, I'll have enough time,
don't worry, I know what I'm doing, I'll get it done by
שבת. Okay, ועבד ולא ספק, va'avad velo safak, and he did the
ברית מילה and he didn't finish it before שבת was
over. ואשתכח דחבורה הוא דעבד, ve'ishtakach dechabbura hu de'avad, so he violated
שבת and he gets כרת. Now what's interesting is, you see a
more interesting question I would ask is, let's say he actually did
it in a way not just he half did it, he did
it in a way that maybe he like really, I don't know
if it's possible unless you really injure the person, do it in
a way where you messed it up that it can't be fixed.
Okay, so in some in a case like that would you say
if you were doing the מצוה and somehow it you now ruined
the
מצוה, are you considered having violated שבת? Or the fact that you
did it with proper license means that even if somehow you ruined
it in the end, you did not violate שבת? So that's one
question. The גמרא has a different scenario. The גמרא says... The conclusion
is that you didn't really have license to do it. You came
in and wanted to do it and you were told there's not
enough time. So you were being irresponsible to try to start the
ברית מילה on שבת and you really did not begin it with
proper license. And therefore, if you did not succeed in finishing it
on שבת, you are held responsible and you are considered to have
violated because you shouldn't have begun it to begin with. But I
do still think the interesting question unanswered is well let's say you
begun it properly, but then you somehow messed up. Right? Would you
still be considered? I'll give you here maybe an easier scenario. I
come to שחט shecht my קרבן פסח on שבת and I slip
in the שחיטה and I just make a big mess, okay? Have
I been מחלל שבת? mechallel shabbos? Right? What happens when you start
with license and not you have to do it, you actually ruin
it? Okay, so something to think about that the גמרא has not
addressed, but the case the גמרא came up with was when you
shouldn't have even begun because you didn't have enough time. Okay, so
what's the משנה Mishna saying?